<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts on Ramesh Sundaram</title>
        <link>https://rameshsundaram.github.io/posts/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Posts on Ramesh Sundaram</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 May 2020 16:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://rameshsundaram.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        <item>
            <title>Hugo and Embedding Tableau Viz in Posts</title>
            <link>https://rameshsundaram.github.io/posts/2020/05/hugo-and-embedding-tableau-viz-in-posts/</link>
            <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2020 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://rameshsundaram.github.io/posts/2020/05/hugo-and-embedding-tableau-viz-in-posts/</guid>
            <description>Have you tried embedding an interactive Tableau visualization in a site generated by Hugo? This short article hopefully helps clarify how to get it done using shortcodes.
What is Hugo If you are reading this, you are reading a site generated by Hugo. It is a really fast way to stand up your static site for blogs or showcasing your portfolio of work.
There are tons and tons of resources for how to do that and below are a couple of articles that helped me.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Have you tried embedding an interactive Tableau visualization in a site generated by Hugo? This short article hopefully helps clarify how to get it done using <a href="https://gohugo.io/content-management/shortcodes/">shortcodes</a>.</p>
<h3 id="what-is-hugo">What is Hugo</h3>
<p>If you are reading this, you are reading a site generated by <a href="https://gohugo.io/">Hugo</a>. It is a really fast way to stand up your <em>static</em> site for blogs or showcasing your portfolio of work.</p>
<p>There are tons and tons of resources for how to do that and below are a couple of articles that helped me.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://dev.to/zaracooper/create-your-developer-portfolio-using-hugo-and-github-pages-35en">How to set up a portfolio site</a></li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/free-code-camp/two-ways-to-deploy-a-public-github-pages-site-from-a-private-hugo-repository-627312ec63b9">CI For Hugo</a></li>
</ul>
<h3 id="what-is-tableau">What is Tableau</h3>
<p>I was introduced to <a href="https://www.tableau.com/">Tableau</a> years ago as a Visualization tool but since then the excellent team in Tableau has added more and more features such that it has now become a data integration, data processing and all around <a href="https://www.tableau.com/learn/series/hardcore-analytics">serious analytics</a> tool. It even has integrations to R and Python so you can integrate your statistical models and render visual results in Tableau.</p>
<p>When you create nifty tableau visualizations, you can share them in <a href="https://public.tableau.com/s/">Tableau Public</a>. You can also embed your visualizations in your web application using their <a href="https://help.tableau.com/current/api/js_api/en-us/JavaScriptAPI/js_api.htm">JavaScript API</a>. For example see what <a href="census.gov">census.gov</a> is attempting to do <a href="https://www.census.gov/library/visualizations/interactive/bfs-weekly-business-applications.html">here</a>.</p>
<h3 id="embedding-tableau-visualizations-in-a-hugo-generated-site">Embedding Tableau Visualizations in a Hugo generated Site</h3>
<p>The power of Hugo to me is rapid development and use of markdown. This allows one to read the content without the markup noise. Shortcodes are extremely useful towards code readability. Shortcodes are simple snippets inside your content files calling built-in or custom templates.</p>
<p>Hugo provides a bunch of custom-built shortcodes. For example, you might want to embed a youtube video in your blogpost. It is done simply through the following</p>
<pre><code>{{&lt; youtube  w7Ft2ymGmfc &gt;}}
</code></pre>
<p>You can also make your own shortcode if you like. The example below embeds a &ldquo;tableau&rdquo; shortcode. However, because it is custom, you need to specify how to render for Hugo .</p>
<pre><code>{{&lt; tableau &quot;https://public.tableau.com/views/TomPettyAnalysis-Moxie/HistoricalJourney?:showVizHome=no&amp;:embed=true&quot; &gt;}}
</code></pre>
<p>The shortcode I created for embedding is a simple <em>iframe</em> with a link to the source.</p>
<pre><code>&lt;iframe src = &quot;{{.Get 0}}&quot; width=&quot;1020&quot; height=&quot;900&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;border: 0px;&quot; scrolling=&quot;yes&quot;&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;
</code></pre>
<p>Save this snippet of code in a tableau.html in your themes/<!-- raw HTML omitted -->/layouts/shortcodes/</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
